Guide to the John Glines Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Glines papers
1800-2017
MS 1895
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
22.28
(59 boxes)
The papers primarily consist of correspondence, writings, theatrical production files, biographical and financial records, journals, memorabilia (including awards and scrapbooks), photographs, photo albums, and audiovisual materials documenting Glines's personal and professional life as a writer for stage and screen, actor, and producer of gay theater. The Glines, the oldest professional gay theater production company in the United States, founded in 1976 by John Glines, Barry Laine, and Jerry Tobin, is also documented.
Glines, John
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John Glines, 2008-2016, and the John Glines Estate, 2018.
Related Materials
The Glines Records (MS 1920). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and four additions: I. Correspondence, circa 1936-2002. II. Writings, circa 1946-1996. III. Theatrical Productions, circa 1949-2002. IV. Personal Papers, 1800-2011.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, theatrical production files, biographical and financial records, journals, memorabilia (including awards and scrapbooks), photographs, and audiovisual materials documenting Glines's personal life, from childhood to adulthood as a gay man, and professional life as a writer for stage and screen, actor, and producer of gay theater. The Glines, the oldest professional gay theater production company in the United States, founded in 1976 by John Glines, Barry Laine, and Jerry Tobin, is also documented. The correspondence emphasizes Glines's relationship with his mother, his maternal grandfather, Horace Lanza, his half-brothers, Bill Owen and Jim Glines, and various Yale classmates. The writings include childhood journals and other manuscripts, drafts of plays, theatrical and television scripts, and some works by others. These offer a particularly rich trove of material, because they document Glines's development as a writer from an early age. The production material documents Glines's development as a writer and actor through his high school, Yale, and post-Yale years, as well as numerous gay theatrical productions in New York City from the 1970s to the 1990s. Although some Glines theater productions are documented in the papers, they are more fully documented in The Glines Records (MS 1920). The biographical information features a Glines family genealogy, birth and other vital records, resumes, and newspaper clippings. Glines's memorabilia consists mainly of high school and college scrapbooks, yearbooks, and awards. The photographs document Glines himself throughout his life (including his travels), as well as his family, friends, lovers, and associates in the New York theater scene.
Biographical / Historical
The American playwright, actor, and producer John Glines aka John Owen (1933-2018) was born John Horace Glines in Santa Maria, California, on October 11, 1933. Nicknamed Tex, he was the only child of Ellen Antoinette Lanza Glines and Denzil Cassius Glines. His parents divorced, and in 1942 his mother was remarried to William Wallace Owen, whose name the family took. Glines grew up in the East Bay area of San Francisco. He attended Piedmont High School and Yale University as John Owen. He graduated from Yale University in 1955 with a Bachelor of Arts degree in drama. In 1962 he returned to using the name John Glines.
During college Owen (as he was then known) appeared with the Yale Dramat in a total of twelve productions as an actor. He played only comedy with the exception of his role in Pirandello's Six Characters in Search of an Author. He acted, for example, in Aristophanes' The Birds, Shaw's Too True to be Good, Shakespeare's The Tempest (Stephano), and Moliere's Tartuffe (Orgon). As head of the Saybrook (his college) Players, he co-authored, composed, directed, and appeared in two musical revues. He also co-authored, co-directed, choreographed, and appeared in a third musical revue called So What!.
Immediately after Yale, Glines went to New York City to be a trainee in the NBC Comedy Writers Development Workshop. During the next several years he would try his hand as stand-up comic, film editor, director, TV extra, and actor. Returning to California, Glines became actor/producer of summer stock, The Comedy Theatre in Oakland in 1956. This equity stock company staged Molnar's The Play's The Thing (Glines playing Mr. Mel); Roussin's The Little Hut; and Shaw's Misalliance (Glines playing Bentley Summerhayes). Back in New York City by late 1956, Glines worked as mail boy and film shipper at Channel 5 (DuMont Broadcasting Company). This led circuitously to his becoming a contract supervisor in the business affairs department of CBS News from 1959 to 1960. He made his professional acting debut Off Broadway as Richard Hare and Lord Mount Severn in an adaptation of Mrs. Henry Wood's novel and play East Lynne, retitled Boo Hoo! East Lynne, staged at Theatre East, New York, 1959. Other Off Broadway performances included the role of Waiter (Walter Boon) in Shaw's You Never Can Tell, the role of Me in the original revue Sam and Me, and the role of Pierre in the fifteenth-century French farce Pierre Patelin (for which he served as translator and adapter) for the short-lived American Theatre Repertory Company. He also performed as an actor-dancer in the original musical-revue Maud and Her Madness and in the revue Sunday Night Music Hall.
In 1960 Glines moved to Brooklyn Heights and worked as a temporary typist, a radiation monitor, and production assistant. About this time he also took courses at the City College of New York (CCNY) at night and worked days as a film editor for Orbit Productions. Glines then turned to directing. He was a director at the Off Broadway Rodale Week-End Theater under J. I. Rodale. In 1963 Glines directed Rodale's comedies Man on the Bridge and A Yugoslav Medical Mystery, as well as Rodale's so-called Biblical musical comedy Stones of Jehoshaphat. In 1964, Glines directed a series of gospel concerts at the U.S. Pavilion at the New York World's Fair. In 1965 he was elected to membership in the American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers.
As a staff writer in children's television, he worked for seven years (1965-1972) on Captain Kangaroo under producer Al Hyslop and for three and a half years (1978-1981) on Sesame Street (during which time he was twice nominated for an Emmy Award). One of his last contributions to Sesame Street was to name the little red Muppet that had just been created: Elmo. He also served as a creative consultant on the Children's Television Workshop show 3-2-1 Contact. In 1966 he served as lyricist of an animated cartoon made to promote the Peanut Growers of Alabama and Georgia; and in 1970 he wrote two animated shorts for McGraw-Hill, Johnny Appleseed and Tepozton.
Glines left Captain Kangaroo to have a musical produced Off Broadway. God Bless Coney, of which he was the author, composer, and lyricist, premiered at the Orpheum, New York, 1972. He then became head writer of a TV series produced by the Appalachia Educational Lab in Charleston, West Virginia; and he wrote for the Ballet Hispanico de Nueva York (circa 1973). He became involved in Off-Off-Broadway as author of The Bells of Hell (a one-act play), author/director of Boy on a Lonely Journey (1975), and then administrative director of playwright Doric Wilson's company, TOSOS (The Other Side of Silence), which had been founded in 1972. He directed The Great American Bike Show, which toured the country in the summer of 1975. Later in 1975 Glines served as head writer for It's Never Too Late, an all-star PBS special for parents of preschoolers. His play In the Desert of My Soul was published by Dramatists Play Service and republished in Stanley Richards's anthology Best Short Plays of 1976.
In 1976 Glines co-founded a not-for-profit organization for gay arts called The Glines. For the first two years The Glines maintained a Tribeca space, producing numerous gay and lesbian plays, cabaret shows, and art exhibits, fulfilling their stated purpose of being a "gay art center." After losing the space in 1978, The Glines became primarily a production company, using various Manhattan theaters to present plays like the world premiere of Doric Wilson's A Perfect Relationship. That summer they staged a revival of Relationship, Robert Patrick's frequently produced The Haunted Host, Richard Hall's Love Match, and Doric Wilson's The West Street Gang at the same Chelsea leather bar (the Spike Bar) where the latter play was originally performed. His musical Gulp!, written with Stephen Greco and Robin Jones, became the longest running Off-Off-Broadway production of 1977. The Glines would later become recognized as the country's oldest producer of gay theater, with Glines himself being acknowledged as a major force in the acceptance of the gay experience as valid material of creative expression.
In 1980-1981 Glines served as co-producer of Jane Chambers's Last Summer at Bluefish Cove Off Broadway (Actors Playhouse) starring Jean Smart, and in 1982 went to Broadway as co-producer of Torch Song Trilogy, which won Tony Awards for Best Play and Best Actor and the Drama Desk Award for Best Play. Torch Song also played three years on Broadway, establishing it as one of the longest running plays on Broadway. During the 1983 Tony Awards, Glines became the first gay person ever to acknowledge his lover on a televised awards show.
Glines subsequently became co-producer of two national companies and a London company. In 1985 he served as co-producer (with Circle Repertory) of the Broadway production of William M. Hoffman's As Is, which was nominated for Tony Awards for Best Play, Best Director, and Best Actor, and won the Drama Desk Award for Best Play of 1985. Glines won the Drama Desk Award for Best Musical Revue in 1994 for Howard Crabtree's and Mark Waldrop's Whoop-Dee-Doo !
Glines's later plays, produced originally by The Glines, were On Tina Tuna Walk, A Comedy (1988), In Her Own Words (A Biography of Jane Chambers) (1989), Men of Manhattan, Scenes of New York City Gay Life (1990), Chicken Delight, A Farce (1992), Body and Soul, A Romantic Comedy (1992), Murder in Disguise, A Comedy Mystery (1992), Key West (1994), Heavenly Days (1996), How Now, Voyager (1997), and Butterflies and Tigers (1998), the last based on true stories of the Chinese people during the Cultural Revolution, 1966 to 1976.
Glines produced The Glines' First and Second Gay American Arts Festivals (1980 and 1981). He also co-produced a murder mystery at the Plaza Hotel for four weeks in the summer of 1986. In 1985, as a result of his work on As Is, he became the originator and project director of the major AIDS fundraising campaign Stamp Out AIDS. This evolved into Broadway Cares/Equity Fights AIDS, of which Glines was a founding trustee and for which he continued to serve on the advisory committee into the 1990s.
Between 1981 and 2000, Glines won numerous awards for his work as a producer, lesbian and gay community builder, and advocate for gay rights. For example, in 1981 he won the Villager Theatre Award as producer of the First Gay American Arts Festival, and in 2000 Howard Golden, the president of the Borough of Brooklyn, chose Glines as one of that year's Lesbian and Gay Pride History Month honorees. Glines died in Bangkok, Thailand on August 8, 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Gay authors; Gay dramatists; Gay men; Gay theater -- United States; Gays and the performing arts; Off-Broadway theater; LGBTQ resource; Glines, John; Glines
- Correspondence, Circa 1936-2002; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence is arranged alphabetically and comprises both incoming letters to Glines and letters from Glines to his mother, Ellen Lanza Owen. The letters document his personal and family life and his life as a high school student and an undergraduate at Yale. To a lesser extent they document his career as a writer and theatrical producer, and his contributions to the gay artistic and political milieu in New York. The most substantive portion of the correspondence concerns Glines's personal life. Of particular interest are his letters to his mother as a young adult. There are no letters documenting his intimate relationships with men.
  - Allen, Maude V. (grand aunt), 1947 July (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers, 1995 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annie, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Armistead, Circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Auntie Mame, 1958 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bate, Dana (Cultural Council Foundation), 1975 August (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Berman, Lois (writer's representative), 1975 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bob, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Borden, Francis (Director of Publicity, Exposition Press), 1949 July (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Burgess, Ken, 1985 December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Burke, Briana, 1994 January (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Campfire Guardians, 1946 October (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Carroll and Debi, 1979 December (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Casey, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Children visitors (students of Mr. Giveans), 1970 June (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chita, 1983 April (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chuck, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cooney, Joan Ganz (Sesame Street colleague), 1980 February (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cox, Christopher (Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company), 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Crosley, Chase, Circa 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Davis, Vera Lee Glines (aunt), 1961 October (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ellen (addressed to "Mrs. John Glines"), Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fortieth birthday, 1973 October (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Foster Parents Plan (Orrala, Walter, foster child), 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Franklin, Sally, 1967 June-1969 December (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Fritsch, Emil ("Teddy"), Circa 1951 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Gaithner, H. Rowan, Jr. (family friend), 1951 April (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Gesner, Clark, 1979 May (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Glines, Anne (half-sister), 1954 Dec, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Glines, Denzil C. (father), Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Glines, Margaret, 1957 December (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Glines, Jim (half-brother), Circa 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "God Bless Coney" (play opening), 1972 April-May (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Greco, Stephen, Circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gwennie and Vincent, 1973 September (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Harvey, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Henderson, James W. (New York Public Library), 1975 October (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hirsch, Edith, 1950 November (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hock, Robert D., 1955 December (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Irene, 1950 November (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Jerry [?], 1981 January (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Jones, Robin (Yale classmate), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Kantrowitz, Arnie, 1991 November (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Kennedy, Edward M., 1984 October (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Kilmurry, Edward J., 1967 September (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Kostus, Ron (Yale classmate), Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - La Paglia, Alfonso and Frank, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Lanza, Horace (grandfather), 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Leo and Ganeille [?], 1965 December (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Leslie, F. Andrew (Dramatists Play Service), 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Lorraine/Laurie (high school girlfriend), 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - MacGregor, Mary (Greenburg Publishers representative), 1949 March (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Marcus, Carlyn, 1969-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - McManus, Marg and Tom (aunt and uncle), 1948 April (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Merchant, Dale, 1988 October (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Miller, Morris and Estelle, 1963 October (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Moss, Bob (Playwrights Horizons), 1975 January (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - National Broadcasting Company, 1956 February (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Noyes, Edward S. (Chairman, Board of Admissions, Yale University), 1951 May (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - O'Brien, John (The One Institute), 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Ortner, Evelyn, Undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Otto, Margrit, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Owen, Bill (half-brother), 1952-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Owen, Ellen Lanza (mother), Circa 1936-1968, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
  - Parker, Gilbert (Curtis Brown, Ltd), 1975 April (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Patrick, Robert, 1993 February (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Paul, 1972 February (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Peg, 2000 June (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Piedmont High School friends and principal, 1950 November-circa 1951 May-August (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rick, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Roberts, Mimi and Lathrop, 1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Robin, Elizabeth, Sasha, Toby, Circa 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sauls, Frederick J. (high school classmate), 1955-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Save The Children Federation, concerning Clitso, Paul (foster child), 1970-1976 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Spitzer, Eliot (Attorney General), 2000 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Steve C., 1994 November (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Steven and Frank, Circa 1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Stoddard, Brandon (Yale classmate), 1956 May (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Swoyer, Nanny, Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Thunen, Mrs. Lewis C. (Church School), 1946 December (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Tirrell, Donald Bailey, 1957-1972, 2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Von Kugelgen, Dr. and Mrs. Robert Leland, 1959-1967 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Williams, Anne, Circa 1948 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Mostly related to theatrical productions, 1960-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Yale-related, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Unidentified, 1966-1979, 2002, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Writings, Circa 1946-1996; Series II
  The series is comprised of original writings by Glines as well as a few writings by others. Glines's writings consists of journals; plays; theatrical, film, and television scripts; song lyrics; and poems written from childhood through adulthood.
  - By Glines
    - General, Circa 1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Contracts and royalties, 1949-1992 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Journals, 1947, 1949 and undated (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
    - Manuscripts
      - "Around the Bend: Yours and Mine", Circa 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - "The Art", Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Articles in Sunday Oakland Tribune, Circa 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - "A Bitch in Amber", 1964 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - "The Blockhead and the Bride", Circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - "Body and Soul", Circa 1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - "Boy on a Lonely Journey", 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Comedy Theatre, 1956 August (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - "Courage" (poem), Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - "Davy Crockett", Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - "The Demonstration", 1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - "Dinosaurs (III)", 1978 November (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Doug Henning Show, 1981 July (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - "Fickle Fingers: An Autobiography", Circa 1996 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - "Films 15" (City College of New York), 1962 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - "Football Players Don't Cry", 1969 or later (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - "The Ghost Train", Circa 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - "God Bless Coney", 1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - "The Greatest Man in the World", [1950s?] (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - "Heavenly Days", 1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - "The Imaginary Invalid" (by Molière), English translation, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - "In Her Own Words (A Biography of Jane Chambers)", 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - "It's Never Too Late", 1975 October (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - "Johnny Appleseed", 1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - "Life in East Aurora or the Lanza-Clan", Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - "The Little Star", 1979 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - "Men of Manhattan", 1989 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Music, 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - "A Musical History of Campaigns, Causes, and Candidates", Circa 1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - "Nightmare in One Act", Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - "On Stage!", 1950 November (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - "Program #2, #3, and #4", Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - "Richmond Rendezvous", Circa 1954 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - "Road Song", Circa 1972 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Sesame Street vignettes, Circa 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Song lyrics (set to popular tunes), Circa 1964 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - "Springtime a la Carte" (by O'Henry), adaptation?, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - "A Star-Spangled Clambake", Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - "Tepozton", 1970 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Theatrical vignettes, Circa 1954, 1961 May, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - "This Has Been John Owen" (poem), Circa 1951-1955 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - "To: Sam Gibbon", 1978 September (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - "Treatment", 1962 March and September (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - "Tweedsdale 22", Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - "Waiter's Sketch," etc., Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - "The Wassail Bowl", Circa 1946-1950 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - "The Wedding of the Season or Here We Go Again!", Undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - "Ye Gods and Little Fishes", Undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Untitled fragment, Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Untitled manuscripts, Circa 1946-1950 (Box 5, Folder 16-17)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Notes, bibliography on American folklore and song and Andrew Jackson, Undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
        - Notes, "Drama 6", Circa 1953 (Box 5, Folder 19)
        - Notes, "Ten Commandments of Dialogue Writing", Undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
        - Notes, "Zodiac", Undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - By Others
    - "Canasta Solitaire" by Alex Andrus, Circa 1956 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - "The Color of a House" by Tennessee Williams, After 1982 August (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - "Desert Reptiles" by Alex Andrus, Circa 1956 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - "The Disintegration of a Secretary or Leading the Lamb to Slaughter" Anonymous, Undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - "Hello Dolly" and untitled manuscript, by Casey Wayne, Circa 1979 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - "Honor is of Man" by Alex Andrus, Circa 1956 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - "Pocahontas" by John Brougham, Esq., Undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Untitled, by Anthony Bruno, 1989 February (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Theatrical Productions, Circa 1949-2002; Series III
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  Copies of commercially produced audiovisual materials contained in this collection cannot be made for researcher use outside of the repository.